<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gradle | ...and they shall know me by my speling errors.]]></title>
  <link href="http://speling.shemnon.com//blog/categories/gradle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://speling.shemnon.com//"/>
  <updated>2012-10-23T22:13:54-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://speling.shemnon.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Danno Ferrin]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[danno.ferrin@shemnon.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a JavaFX Gradle Plugin]]></title>
    <link href="http://speling.shemnon.com//blog/2012/10/17/javafx-gradle-plugin/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T22:47:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://speling.shemnon.com//blog/2012/10/17/javafx-gradle-plugin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to get this out there early, since "release early release often" is one of the open source mantras.  I have a longer blog post planned on this subject, but I have so many balls in the air right now I'm not sure when I'll get to write it.</p>

<p>I am starting to write a <a href="https://bitbucket.org/shemnon/javafx-gradle">JavaFX 2.0 Gradle Plugin</a> over at bitbucket.  Right now it handles just the <code>fx:jar</code> and <code>fx:deploy</code> ant tasks.  And not completely. I don't have the resources wired into the native bundles.  But that will come.  I also am not doing binary CSS or Jar signing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two samples in the repo demonstrating the build.  I pulled from the JavaFX 2.2.0 Samples brickbreaker and Ensemble2 which represents a small and large project. I moved the files around into a conventional layout, and provided the barest of Gradle scripts I could, with the help of the plugin.  The script for <a href="https://bitbucket.org/shemnon/javafx-gradle/src/4f1f197a845d5fccc4408ad3c49167e65421b1df/brickbreaker/build.gradle?at=master">brickbreaker</a> is awesomely short.  And <a href="https://bitbucket.org/shemnon/javafx-gradle/src/955cc9b99dc86c3b384b40157801ffd3c1adfe94/Ensemble2/build.gradle?at=master">Ensemble2</a> is a bit longer because of the custom build work it is doing to bring the source of the samples into the jar.  When you run 'gradle assemble` it will actually create the Mac OSX .app and .dmg files.  It probably does the correct thing on Linux and Windows but I haven't tried yet.  But first you need to install the plugin via 'gradle install' in the plugin dir.</p>

<p><strong>Conventions</strong></p>

<p>My main purpose in this exercise is to try and nail down a set of file layout conventions that Gradle and Maven can use to create a shippable app with a minimum of configuration.  Layouts that match the Maven way for the most part.  And Ant scripts can be written to these conventions.  If, you know, Ant is your thing.</p>

<p>The only out there conventions would be the bundle resources, which I am placing in <code>src/main/resources</code>.  I also intend to add some other standard files, like <code>src/main/resources/icon.png</code> and associated files and directories being loaded into the proper place for native bundling.  I also need to figure out what to do about signing keys.  Likely this will have to be a configuration thing since checking in your signing key to source control would be a bad idea, even if you have the world's most awesome password.</p>

<p>Finally, I have zero intention of writing this hypothetical Maven plugin. Gradle is what I do for fun. I'de rather write Perl scripts than Maven plugins, no offense to the Perl crowd. But being part of the conversation to set the conventions is something I intend to be a part of.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
